Register of the Sergei Sergeevich Tolstov Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Sergei Sergeevich Tolstov papers
1914-1940
2000C65
Hoover Institution Archives
2 microfilm reels (0.3 linear feet)
Correspondence, military documents, and photographs, relating to Russian military activities during World War I, and to the Russian Civil War.
Tolstov, Sergei Sergeevich, 1881-
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Colonel S. S. Tolstov was born on 13 February 1881. He was wounded in the Russo-Japanese War and several times in the course of the First World War, where he began as a captain and rose to command the 5th Siberian Rifles (promoted to the rank of colonel in 1916).
In 1917, as commander of the 6th Siberian Reserve Brigade, he was simultaneously the commander of the Krasnoiarsk garrison and later the entire military region. Arrested during the anti-Bolshevik uprising in Irkutsk in December 1917, he escaped from jail to Vladivostok, where he worked in various capacities. In June 1918, he was invited by the anti-Bolshevik government in Vladivostok to be commander of the Primor'e Military District. In September 1918, he resigned his command for political reasons and left for Shanghai (1919). In 1923 he and his wife, Lidiia Vladislavovna, moved to San Francisco, where he was involved in fundraising activity to help Russian war invalids abroad, and where he died of a heart attack on 9 November 1950.
Chronology
1881 February 13 (O.S.) Born, Kazanskaia guberniia, Russia
1898 Entered military service as a volunteer
1901 Graduated Kazan' infantry military college
1904-1905 Served in Russo-Japanese War with 6 th Eniseiskii polk
1914-1915 Commanded mounted unit of 2 nd Siberian Rifle Division
1915-1916 Battalion commander, 5 th Eastern Siberian Rifles
1917 Commanded 15 th Siberian Reserve Regiment Commanded 6 th Siberian Rifle Brigade Commanded Krasnoiarsk garrison
1918 Commanded military and naval forces of the Maritime District Commandant, Vladivostok fortress
1919 April Arrived, Shanghai, China
1923 Arrived, United States
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Colonel Sergei Sergeevich Tolstov detail his military career during the First World War and Russian Civil War. They include orders, battlefield notes and descriptions of battles on the Austrian front of World War I, and in Siberia and the Far East (Vladivostok) during the period 1917-1919. The correspondence is also largely of a military nature.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Russia. Armiia--Officers; Russia.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; World War, 1914-1918.
- Biographical File, 1914-1933 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Letters of recommendation, military service records and other materials, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1923-1938 (Box 1)
  Letters and cards from unidentified individuals
- Subject File, 1914-1940 (Box 1-2)
  Correspondence, orders, military service records, battle dispositions and field notes, and other materials, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Photographs, 1910s-1930s(?) (Box 2)
  Sixteen prints depicting S. S. Tolstov, other officers, scenes from the First World War and unidentified individuals
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1914-1933 (Box 1)
  - Commendations.
    General note
    See SUBJECT FILE/World War, 1914-1918--Veterans--Russia
  - Letters of recommendation from G. Elliot and V. Grosse (Folder 1: 1)
  - Military service records. (Folder 1: 2)
    See also SUBJECT FILE
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 3)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1923-1938 (Folder 1: 4)
  Letters and cards from unidentified individuals, 1923-1938
- SUBJECT FILE, 1914-1940
  - Obukhov, Vladimir Dimitrievich (Folder 1: 5)
  - Russia (Territory under White Armies, )., 1918-1920 (Folder 1: 6-8)
    - Armiia.
      Documents relating to the Civil War in the Maritime District, particularly the situation in Vladivostok in 1918, consisting mainly of correspondence, recommendations, orders, and related matter
  - World War, 1914-1918
    - Campaigns--Eastern Front. (Folder 1: 9-11)
      Orders, descriptions of battles, field books
    - Russia. (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
      Correspondence from soldiers and fellow officers, 1914-1917, and orders relating to Tolstov's service in Krasnoiarsk in 1917
    - Veterans--Russia. (Folder 2: 3-4)
      Mainly correspondence relating to military invalids outside Russia, 1931-1940. Includes commendations to Tolstov for his part in aiding them
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1910s-1930s(?) (Folder 2: 5)
  16 prints depicting S. S. Tolstov, episodes of his life, family members, and friends